Amelia Marie Smith

:: ameliamsmith10@gmail.com:: 115 Kleyona Avenue Phoenixville, PA 19460 :: 610.496.8606. ::

Professional Summary

Highly motivated and energetic teaching professional seeks an opportunity to showcase her knowledge of broad skill development for reading and writing in the content areas and supporting content area teachers with necessary skill scaffolding to achieve the goal of independent, college ready learners.

Certifications

Elementary Education K-6, Instructional I (PA and MD)

Special Education Certification PK-8 (PA)

Reading Specialist K-12 and ESL K-8 (anticipated finish: Spring 2016) (PA)

Middle School ELA 6-8 (passed required Praxis examination 2013)

Skills Summary

Technology – Mac, iPad, Pages, Google Drive, Dropbox, Turnitin, Promethean Software, SmartTechnology, Microsoft Office Suite, Study Island, Notability, PowerSchool

Education Programs – Read Naturally, Wilson Fundations, Dibels, Readers Workshop, DRA, Fountas and Pinnell, Junior Great Books, LLI, Everyday Mathematics, Book Club, Literature Circles, Words Their Way, Journey's, envisionMath, Interactive Science, experience using MLA and APA formatting, PSAT and SAT prep, Benchmarking as well as developing traceable improvement plans

Professional Experience

Villa Maria Academy High School, Malvern PA (June 2015 to Present) Learning Specialist, ESL Program Coordinator and Teacher, SSD Coordinator

- Developed and implemented curriculum for 9th grade language preparatory class, which was designed to provide students a with a directed, guided study course in support of their coursework in core classes.
- Provided direct instruction in specific cognitive study strategies to 9th grade language preparatory classes to lay a foundation for success in the high school years
- Launched English as a Second Language program for over 20 international students from China
- Developed and implemented ESL curriculum for international students who have recently entered the school need to learn English in order to be successful in an increasingly competitive global society
- Taught ESL students American cultural traditions, such as holidays and American family traditions; etiquette and classroom behavior; and character traits, such as honesty and punctuality, which are expected of students studying in the United States.
- Supported and supplemented the instruction ESL students received in their core classes.
- Built students' proficiency in listening, reading, speaking, and writing via lessons in American culture using feedback from classroom teachers
- Fulfilled the responsibilities of the College Board SSD testing coordinator; contacting parents and students in order to maintain up to date IEP, 504 and ER files and request the appropriate testing accommodations for over 50 students.

Universal Institute Charter School, Philadelphia, PA (August 2014-June 2015) 2nd Grade Elementary School Teacher

- Responsible for all instructional design and implementation of UICS Grade 2 curriculum over all content domains (Science, Social Studies, Math, Language Arts) incorporating multiple teaching styles to intensify the range of learning
- Managed a classroom of 25 students in an urban setting at the highest level of poverty
- Designed lessons to meet the diverse needs of all learners and made the lessons culturally relevant to all students
- Developed lessons with a focus toward the PA common core curricular targets along with a mind toward incorporating direct process instruction
- Coordinated data in order to track students' progress using Benchmarks, DRA, Fountas and Pinnell
- Participated in Children's Literacy Initiative training and group coaching to incorporate CLI into the classrooms at UICS
- Delivered differentiated language arts instruction utilizing the Balance Literacy approach using the Reader's Workshop Guided reading model and the Writer's Workshop model for writing

- Managed a whole classroom behavior modification plan as a motivator to improve conduct and encourage participation for both individual, small group and whole group behaviors for 25 students
- Advocated for students with emotional, behavioral and education needs to assure their needs were met
- Developed a strong and open communication system with parents to create an educational partnership between home and school
- Coordinated field trips for the entire 2nd grade to enhance concepts, provide culturally enriching experiences and to motivate students to want to learn more
- Co-chair of the K-8 talent show
- Member of the school Celebrations Committee to enhance school culture and spirit
- Organized school-wide book swap program for students in grades PK-8

Perkiomen Valley School District, Collegeville, PA (November 2011 to August 2014)

Extended Daily Substitute Teacher, Spanish K-5 (January 2014-June 2014)

• Implemented lessons, in Spanish, provided by the regular classroom teacher

Long Term Substitute Teacher, 2nd grade (August 2012-January 2013)

- Responsible for all instructional design and implementation of PVSD Grade 2 curriculum over all content domains (Science, Social Studies, Math, Language Arts) incorporating multiple teaching styles to intensify the range of learning
- Developed lessons with a focus toward the PA common core curricular targets along with a mind toward incorporating direct process instruction
- Managed a classroom behavior modification plan as a motivator to improve conduct and encourage participation for both individual and whole group behaviors for 21 students
- Coordinated all special student support needs with building support team
- Delivered differentiated language arts instruction utilizing the Reader's Workshop Guided reading model
- Produced standards-based grade reporting
- Assisted with the formulation of Individual Education Programs

Classroom Teacher, Pre-First Grade Summer Program (Summer 2013)

Utilized strategies for emergent literacy across a wide range of instructional delivery methods

Elementary Instructional Paraprofessional (November 2011-June 2012, January 2013-August 2014)

- Implemented Junior Great Books program for advanced readers
- Participated in data meetings and contributed to discussions about leveling decisions
- Served as building substitute for grades K-5 including autistic support, learning support, and special area classes
- Provided in-class support for struggling and/or enrichment students during math instruction for grades 1st 5th
- Planned and led before school PSSA intervention program using Study Island program (Go-Time!)
- Proctored small group PSSA and 4Sight tests
- Administered DRA tests (Level 1 70), High Frequency Word assessments and Math Benchmark assessments (grades K-1st)
- Instructed an ELL with Level 0 English Using the Wilson Fundations System

Great Valley School District, Instructional Aide (September 2010 to November 2011)

- Organized and reviewed materials with students for skill reinforcement
- Contributed remedial educational and instructional strategies supported instructional staff 2

Phoenixville Area YMCA Assistant Swim Coach (May 2007 to August 2010)

- Assisted head coach with instructing athletes with the rules, regulations equipment and techniques of the sport
- Organized and directed individual and small group practices as directed by the head coach
- Assessed swimmer's skills during competition and practice, and keeps the head coach informed of the athletic performance of swimmers
- Assisted with determining meet strategy
- Assisted the head coach with supervising athletes during practices and competition
- Modeled sports-like behavior and maintained appropriate conduct towards students, officials, and spectators

- Mentored student athletes to help them develop and reach their goals
- Coached athletes from the club to nationally competitive level

Kent County Public School August 2009 to May 2010

Worton, MD

• Student Teaching, 4th Grade

Spring Ford School District

October 2013-August 2014

Royersford, PA

• Reading Specialist Student Teaching, 5th-6th grade

Elwyn School

May 2014-August 2014

Media, PA

Special Education Student Teaching, Autistic Support Early Intervention Preschool Program

Professional Development

- Professional Development Workshops: "Strategies to Help Students Become More Independent", "Formative Assessment", "PV Teacher Supervision and PA Educator Effectiveness Model", "What You Need to Know About the Common Core, and Developing Common Core Resources", "Wilson Fundations Workshop"
- Completed Perkiomen Valley School District's New Teacher Induction Program
- Completed Universal Companies and Villa Maria Academy High School's New Teacher Induction Program
- American Reading Company's "Educating Black and Latino Boys" presented by Dr. Peter Noguera
- Certified in Project WET

Education

Washington College, Chestertown, MD

Bachelors of Arts in Human Development, Elementary Education Concentration, May 2010 Academic All-American Honors, 2010

Cabrini College, Radnor, PA

Special Education Teaching Certificate PK-8, August 2014

Arcadia University, Glenside, PA

Masters in Reading, with Reading Specialist and ESL Program Specialist Certificates, anticipated certification completion Spring 2016

Community Service

- Coached Special Olympics Swimmers, 2006-2010
- Introduced the Adopt-A-Bear Christmas gift program to the Swim and Crew Teams
- Coordinated the Chestertown "Sneaker Creeper Run "for Ages 0-12 to promote Lung Cancer Awareness
- Developed Swim Quest, a swim meet for physically disabled children and adults
- Volunteered as a moderator/scorekeeper for Montgomery County Reading Olympics

Awards & Recognitions

Washington College, Chestertown, MD

- Dean's List
- Varsity Swim Team Captain
- Academic All-American in Swimming
- Varsity Crew Team Spirit Award 2009/2010
- Competed in NCAA D3 Rowing Championships 2008/2009
- All MARC Varsity Team
- Varsity Crew and Swim Team Member 2006-2010